[Sharp Blade in the Snow]
[نصل حاد في الثلج]
[Episode 24]
[الحلقة 24]
I already have gray hair.
شعري رمادي بالفعل.
I'm really getting old.
أشعر حقاً أنني أتقدم في السن.
Your Highness, you've been worrying over state affairs day and night.
يا صاحب السمو، لقد كنتم قلقين بشأن شؤون الدولة ليلاً ونهاراً.
This is merely a momentary sign of fatigue.
هذه مجرد علامة مؤقتة على التعب.
In my eyes,
في نظري،
Your Highness is as graceful as ever,
صاحب السمو يتمتع برشاقة لا تزال كما عهدتموها،
without a trace of aging.
بدون أي أثر للشيخوخة.
Shaman, you really do know
يا شامان، أنت تعرف حقاً
how to sweet-talk me.
كيف تُغريني بالكلام المعسول؟
Those are my true feelings—
تلك هي مشاعري الحقيقية.
no flattery in it at all.
لا يوجد فيها أي تملق على الإطلاق.
Once the wedding is complete tomorrow
بمجرد اكتمال حفل الزفاف غداً
and the position of Queen of Mocheng changes hands,
وتغير منصب ملكة موتشنغ ،
Your Highness can truly rule the realm
سموكم قادرون حقاً على حكم المملكة
in peace.
بسلام.
Unfortunately,
للأسف،
the Tiger Tally remains unfound.
لا يزال عدد النمور غير معروف.
No matter how perfect the plan,
مهما كانت الخطة مثالية،
without military authority to back it,
بدون سلطة عسكرية تدعم ذلك،
it's nothing more than a castle in the air.
إنها ليست سوى قصر في الهواء.
I've sent people to infiltrate the Bai Residence,
أرسلتُ رجالاً للتسلل إلى مقر إقامة باي،
but there's no sign of the Tiger Tally
لكن لا يوجد أي أثر لـ "إحصاء النمور"
found on Feng Li.
تم العثور عليه في فنغ لي.
It seems I'll have to
يبدو أنني سأضطر إلى
take matters into my own hands.
سأتولى الأمور بنفسي.
So Bai Yu has taken good care of you, Li.
إذن، لقد اعتنى بك باي يو جيداً يا لي.
After only a few days here,
بعد بضعة أيام فقط هنا،
even your complexion has improved.
حتى بشرتك تحسنت.
How much longer do you plan
إلى متى تخططون؟
to keep up this act?
للحفاظ على هذا التمثيل؟
Li,
الذي - التي،
I'm running out of patience.
لقد نفد صبري.
Hand over the Tiger Tally.
سلّموا لنا جدول إحصائيات النمور.
It'll benefit us both.
سيعود ذلك بالفائدة علينا جميعاً.
What are you doing?
ماذا تفعل؟
Li's already in this state!
لي موجود بالفعل في هذه الحالة!
Why are you still forcing her?
لماذا ما زلت تجبرها؟
All of you, get out!
اخرجوا جميعاً!
I can't bring myself to lay a hand on her,
لا أستطيع أن أجبر نفسي على مد يدي عليها.
but that doesn't mean I would spare you.
لكن هذا لا يعني أنني سأرحمك.
Do it!
افعلها!
Li,
الذي - التي،
hand over the Tiger Tally.
سلّم إحصاء النمور.
Otherwise,
خلاف ذلك،
his other hand
يده الأخرى
won't be spared either.
ولن ينجو أحد أيضاً.
Li,
الذي - التي،
don't listen to her!
لا تستمع إليها!
Ignore her!
تجاهلها!
I didn't expect you to be this cold, Li.
لم أتوقع أن تكون بهذه البرودة يا لي.
Lu Ran.
لو ران.
Do it again.
كرر ذلك.
Do you intend to
هل تنوي أن
keep silent
التزم الصمت
until he's dead?
حتى يموت؟
Your Highness,
صاحب السمو،
the Xiqi delegation has entered the imperial city
دخل وفد شي تشي المدينة الإمبراطورية
and is waiting at the palace gate to be summoned.
وهو ينتظر عند بوابة القصر ليتم استدعاؤه.
At such a critical time?
في مثل هذا الوقت الحرج؟
Your Highness,
صاحب السمو،
since we've got her in our custody,
بما أنها تحت رعايتنا،
getting the Tiger Tally is only a matter of time.
إن الحصول على إحصاء النمور مسألة وقت لا أكثر.
Let it be for now.
لنترك الأمر كما هو الآن.
The wedding tomorrow
حفل الزفاف غداً
is what matters most.
هذا هو الأهم.
Li,
الذي - التي،
be wise.
كن حكيماً.
I'll be back.
سأعود.
I hope that by then,
آمل أن يكون ذلك بحلول ذلك الوقت،
you'll have thought it through.
ستكون قد فكرت في الأمر جيداً.
Li,
الذي - التي،
don't be afraid.
لا تخف.
As long as you stay with me,
طالما بقيت معي،
everything will pass.
كل شيء سيمر.
Please rest here for the moment, Your Excellency.
تفضل بالراحة هنا في الوقت الحالي، يا صاحب السعادة.
Everyone else has also been properly accommodated.
وقد تم توفير أماكن إقامة مناسبة للجميع أيضاً .
To ensure the safety of the Xiqi delegation,
لضمان سلامة وفد شي تشي،
the palace will assign guards to escort you at all times.
سيقوم القصر بتعيين حراس لمرافقتك في جميع الأوقات.
Escort?
مرافقة؟
This is clearly surveillance.
هذا تجسس واضح.
Who's there?
من هناك؟
Hold on.
يتمسك.
It's me,
هذا أنا،
Feng Ling'er.
فنغ لينغ إير.
Feng Ling'er?
فنغ لينغ إير؟
Princess Ling of Mocheng?
الأميرة لينغ من موتشنغ؟
Why are you here?
لماذا أنت هنا؟
This is your sister Xin Miao's token.
هذه هدية تذكارية من أختك شين مياو.
She asked me to come find you
طلبت مني أن آتي لأجدك
to coordinate tomorrow's wedding plan.
لتنسيق خطة حفل الزفاف غداً.
She can't get out right now.
لا تستطيع الخروج الآن.
We can only rely on ourselves.
لا يمكننا الاعتماد إلا على أنفسنا.
How is Xin Miao doing?
كيف حال شين مياو؟
Do you know what the plan is?
هل تعرف ما هي الخطة؟
Rest assured.
اطمئن، لا تشغل بالك.
She's staying safely at my residence.
إنها تقيم بأمان في منزلي.
As for the plan,
أما بالنسبة للخطة،
I don't have time to explain it to you now.
ليس لدي وقت لأشرح لك ذلك الآن.
Once you leave here,
بمجرد مغادرتك من هنا،
go meet Xin Miao.
اذهب لمقابلة شين مياو.
She'll go over everything with you in detail.
ستشرح لك كل شيء بالتفصيل.
What's this about?
ما هذا؟
What do you think?
ماذا تعتقد؟
Changing clothes, obviously.
تغيير الملابس، بالطبع.
You put on my dress,
لقد ارتديت فستاني،
and I'll stay here in your place.
وسأبقى هنا في مكانك.
How else are you supposed to get out?
كيف يُفترض بك أن تخرج من هنا؟
You're a grown man.
أنت رجل بالغ.
Why are you being so fussy?
لماذا أنتِ متطلبة للغاية؟
Are all Xiqi men like this?
هل جميع رجال شي تشي هكذا؟
You rude woman.
يا لكِ من امرأة وقحة.
You...
أنت...
Turn around already.
استدر الآن.
This outfit actually
هذا الزي في الواقع
suits you quite well.
يناسبك هذا تماماً.
Look at
انظر إلى
our reflection in the mirror.
انعكاسنا في المرآة.
Don't we look just like
ألا نبدو متشابهين تماماً؟
an ordinary mother and daughter?
أم وابنتها العاديتان؟
My obedient daughter,
ابنتي المطيعة،
so well-behaved,
حسن السلوك للغاية،
never making a fuss,
لا يثير ضجة أبداً،
letting me dress her up
دعني ألبسها
and sending her off to get married.
وإرسالها للزواج.
What a pity—
يا للأسف-
you're not her after all.
أنت لست هي في النهاية.
No blood ties, no memories,
لا روابط دم، ولا ذكريات.
just an identical face.
وجه مطابق تماماً.
Perhaps it's for the best that you aren't her.
ربما من الأفضل ألا تكوني هي.
Tomorrow,
غداً،
you'll don Feng Li's wedding dress,
سترتدين فستان زفاف فينغ لي،
take her place at the wedding,
حلّ محلها في حفل الزفاف،
and then
وثم
die in her stead.
يموتون بدلاً منها.
Why did you put yourself through this?
لماذا عرّضت نفسك لهذا؟
You are Feng Li?
هل أنت فنغ لي؟
So...
لذا...
So it was all a lie.
إذن، كان الأمر كله كذبة.
You never
أنت لا
belonged to me.
كان ملكي.
Bai!
نعم!
You're afraid of dying,
أنت تخاف من الموت،
aren't you?
أليس كذلك؟
Then help me finish this final act,
ثم ساعدني في إنهاء هذا الفصل الأخير،
and everything will be yours.
وسيكون كل شيء ملكك.
[Courtesy Consists in Respect]
[الأدب يكمن في الاحترام]
I'm afraid there are ominous signs.
أخشى أن هناك علامات تنذر بالسوء.
This marriage is ill-fated.
هذا الزواج مشؤوم.
The heavens are warning us!
السماء تحذرنا!
When mortals deceive their ruler,
عندما يخدع البشر حاكمهم،
Heaven and Earth will not tolerate it!
السماء والأرض لن تتسامحا مع ذلك!
Calamity has befallen us
لقد حلت بنا المصيبة
all because someone is impersonating another
كل ذلك بسبب انتحال شخص ما لشخصية شخص آخر
at this wedding!
في هذا الزفاف!
The Young Master of Xiqi is,
السيد الشاب لـ Xiqi هو،
in truth, a woman in disguise.
في الحقيقة، امرأة متنكرة.
This is Xiqi deceiving our Mocheng!
هذا هو شي تشي يخدع موتشنغ خاصتنا!
What? It's fake?
ماذا؟ إنه مزيف؟
How could that be?
كيف يمكن أن يكون ذلك؟
Stop talking nonsense!
توقف عن قول الهراء!
Xiqi sincerely wishes
تتمنى شي تشي من صميم قلبها
to ally with Mocheng.
للتحالف مع موتشنغ.
How could we possibly hide or deceive?
كيف يمكننا أن نخفي أو نخدع؟
If it's true,
إذا كان ذلك صحيحاً،
why not take off that mask in public?
لماذا لا تخلع ذلك القناع في الأماكن العامة؟
That's right.
هذا صحيح.
Exactly.
بالضبط.
Young Master!
يا سيدي الشاب!
The Mocheng troops
قوات موتشنغ
have surrounded the black jade
أحاطت باليشم الأسود
we brought from Xiqi,
أحضرناها من شيقي،
claiming they were ordered to guard it
زاعمين أنهم تلقوا أوامر بحراسته.
and that no one is to touch it without permission!
وأنه لا يجوز لأحد أن يلمسه دون إذن!
Li and I are deeply in love and of one mind.
أنا ولي مغرمان ببعضنا بشدة ومتفقان في الرأي.
She would never act this way.
هي لن تتصرف بهذه الطريقة أبداً.
It was my order.
كان هذا طلبي.
[Courtesy Consists in Respect]
[الأدب يكمن في الاحترام]
Greetings, Your Highness.
تحية طيبة، صاحب السمو.
What's your intention in this, Princess Royal?
ما هي نيتك من وراء هذا يا أميرة الملكة؟
If you truly wish to wed,
إذا كنت ترغب حقًا في الزواج،
then take off your mask.
ثم انزع قناعك.
If you've got nothing to hide,
إذا لم يكن لديك ما تخفيه،
why fear showing your face?
لماذا تخشى إظهار وجهك؟
Mocheng has mobilized troops to besiege our delegation without telling us.
حشدت موشينغ قواتها لمحاصرة وفدنا دون إخبارنا.
Is this how you treat
هل هذه هي معاملتكم؟
your guests from Xiqi?
ضيوفك من شيقي؟
You clearly committed wrongdoing first,
لقد ارتكبتَ خطأً واضحاً أولاً،
and now you try to deny it?
والآن تحاول إنكار ذلك؟
This Queen in front of us
هذه الملكة التي أمامنا
is an impostor.
إنه دجال.
Since she returned from Xiqi,
منذ عودتها من شي تشي،
she has remained silent and acted timidly,
لقد التزمت الصمت وتصرفت بخجل.
failing to display the dignity of a ruler.
عدم إظهار كرامة الحاكم.
Clearly, it was a scheme by Xiqi
من الواضح أنها كانت خطة من شي تشي
to replace our Queen of Mocheng
لاستبدال ملكة موتشنغ
with an impostor.
مع شخص منتحل لشخصية أخرى.
A mute woman has been impersonating our Queen,
امرأة خرساء تنتحل شخصية ملكتنا،
using the pretense of marriage alliance
باستخدام ذريعة التحالف الزوجي
to scheme against the foundations of our state.
للتآمر ضد أسس دولتنا.
Both the Queen herself
الملكة نفسها
and her carefully plotted actions
وأفعالها المخطط لها بعناية
reveal her treacherous intentions!
اكشفوا عن نواياها الخائنة!
That's right.
هذا صحيح.
But she looks exactly like the Queen.
لكنها تشبه الملكة تماماً.
This...
هذا...
Enough!
كافٍ!
Meng Wu.
منغ وو.
That thing you want
ذلك الشيء الذي تريده
is in my hands.
الأمر بيدي.
This grand play
هذه المسرحية الرائعة
has finally reached its climax.
لقد بلغت ذروتها أخيراً.
You've plotted for years
لقد خططت لسنوات
for this final battle.
لهذه المعركة الأخيرة.
I'll grant your wish.
سأحقق أمنيتك.
I played along with your scheme
لقد سايرتُ خطتك.
just to see
فقط لأرى
how low you could actually sink.
إلى أي مدى يمكنك أن تغرق فعلاً.
Stay calm.
حافظ على هدوئك.
We still have a chance for revenge.
لا تزال لدينا فرصة للانتقام.
Dongli's loyalists still obey my commands.
لا يزال أتباع دونغلي المخلصون يطيعون أوامري.
They'll create chaos when the time comes,
سيخلقون الفوضى عندما يحين الوقت.
and I'll have them escort you out of the palace first.
وسأطلب منهم مرافقتك خارج القصر أولاً.
As long as we're still alive,
ما دمنا على قيد الحياة،
the game is not over.
لم تنتهِ اللعبة بعد.
Your Highness.
صاحب السمو.
Now that we've learned the truth,
والآن بعد أن عرفنا الحقيقة،
we swear to follow you to the death,
نقسم أننا سنتبعك حتى الموت.
Your Highness!
يا صاحب السمو!
How dare you betray me!
كيف تجرؤ على خيانتي!
It was you who betrayed Dongli.
أنت من خنت دونغلي.
You conspired with Meng Wu,
لقد تآمرت مع منغ وو،
murdered my parents, and seized my kingdom.
قتل والديّ، واستولى على مملكتي.
Today,
اليوم،
I'll make you pay for it in blood!
سأجعلك تدفع ثمن ذلك بالدم!
Here.
هنا.
Guards.
حراس.
Strip Meng Wu of her title as Princess Royal
تجريد مينغ وو من لقب الأميرة الملكية
and imprison her in the Imperial Ancestral Temple
وسجنها في المعبد الإمبراطوري للأجداد
to reflect on her sins. She shall never leave without permission.
لتتأمل في ذنوبها. ولن تغادر أبداً دون إذن.
This play
هذه المسرحية
has finally come to an end.
لقد انتهى الأمر أخيراً.
I once believed
كنت أعتقد ذات مرة
that fighting against heaven,
ذلك القتال ضد السماء،
against people,
ضد الناس،
and against the injustice
وضد الظلم
imposed upon women in this world
فرضت على النساء في هذا العالم
was victory.
كان ذلك انتصاراً.
But when I ascended to the throne
لكن عندما اعتليت العرش
and held power over life and death,
وكان يملك سلطة على الحياة والموت،
I finally realized
أدركت أخيراً
that power knows no gender—
إن القوة لا تعرف جنسًا.
only right and wrong.
الصواب والخطأ فقط.
What I've wanted to see
ما كنت أرغب في رؤيته
is not a world turned upside down,
ليس عالماً انقلب رأساً على عقب،
but one where everyone can
لكنها واحدة حيث يمكن للجميع
live with dignity
عِش بكرامة
and be true to themselves.
وأن يكونوا صادقين مع أنفسهم.